Go, today's דף ל"ה, Daf Lamed Heh, two days before מתן תורה,
Mattan Torah, מתן תורה. Mattan Torah. Anyway,
forty-eighth day in the עומר, Omer, we pick up on the bottom
of or the middle of ל"ד עמוד ב' Lamed Dalet Amud Bet
and we're continuing to work our way through the משנה. Mishnah. So
we first had a question about whether when you throw the blood,
a פסול pussul person throws the blood, does it make the remnant
of the blood no longer שיריים, shirayim, no longer able to be
used for doing זריקת הדם? zrikas hadam? And now we go on
to the next part of the משנה Mishnah where it says that
if various invalid people do it, you can go ahead, it doesn't
invalidate the קרבן, korban, not do it like the conveying of the
blood or whatever, it doesn't invalidate the קרבן, korban, just do a
redo. Okay. קיבל הכשר ונתן לפסול. Kibbel Hakasher Venatan Lapussul. A כשר
kasher person gave it to an invalid person, the invalid person gives
it back to the כשר, kasher, do a redo, it didn't invalidate
the קרבן. korban. It was more like it was nothing. And then
it has a list of scenarios. The גמרא's Gemara going to say
צריכא, tzricha, you need all the scenarios. דאשמעינן, D'ishmi'inan, פסול, pussul, if
it had given us the example of an invalid person, הוי אמינא,
havai amina, what פסול? pussul? טמא, tamei, that the invalid person means
specifically a טמא tamei person. And then I would have had a
way to limit that and say because it's a more, because the
problem isn't as weighty in certain ways, that's why it doesn't invalidate.
Why is טמא tamei not as weighty? דחזי לעבודת ציבור, D'chazi laavodat
tzibur, because if the majority of the community is טמא tamei and
you have to bring a regular fixed-time קרבן, korban, you can bring
it even בטומאה. bitumah. So since there are times when טומאה tumah
is allowed, if you did something בטומאה, bitumah, it didn't invalidate, and
it didn't validate, but it didn't invalidate, and go do it again.
שמאלו, Smolo, but if you put it from your right hand to
your left hand, right? דלא, Dlo, maybe that would actively invalidate because
you're never allowed to use your left hand for even for a
fixed קרבן. korban. So the גמרא Gemara says דאשמעינן ve-ashmi'inan שמאלו, smolo,
if it had just given us that example, דחזי הכשר ביום הכפורים,
de-chazei hechsher beyom hakippurim, no, but there is one day and one
קרבן korban that you're allowed to use your left hand. On יום
כיפור Yom Kippur when he brings the fire pan and the incense
with both of his hands, one with one and one with the
other. So because there is one case where left hand is permitted,
maybe also that's why it doesn't have the power to actively invalidate.
I think you need two right hands.
Yeah, right. אבל כלי חול לא, Aval kli chol lo, but if
it had just given us the example of a non-sanctified vessel in
use, which is never allowed, I might say that that actively, I
would have said the same law wouldn't apply and that a non-sanctified
vessel would actively invalidate. דאשמעינן Ve-ashmi'inan כלי חול kli chol if it
had just given us that example, משום דחזי לקדישינהו, mishum dechazi lakadishinu,
that's because it's, there's, it can be fixed. Just say some words,
sanctify it, presto. So that's why it's not seen as an active
invalidity. אבל הנך, Aval hanach, but being טמא tamei or using your
left hand, אימא לא, eima lo, you can't, well טמא tamei you
go to the מקוה, mikvah, but it's not as easy to fix,
okay, and your left hand you can't turn it into your right
hand. So I might think that those things do actively invalidate. צריכא,
Tzricha, that's why you needed all those scenarios. No matter what the
invalidity, if it's not something like the throwing of the blood, if
it's some other type of a thing, so if it's done invalidly,
it doesn't, the קרבן korban isn't כשר, kasher, but it's not actively
invalid, so just do it again if it could be done again.
Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ולא הוי ליה דחוי.
Velay havay lay dechuy. Why don't we apply, this is obviously, דחוי
dechuy is like one of those regular things that you can't get
away from in קדשים, Kodshim, the same way like פיגול pigul and
דחוי dechuy are like two of these things that you never can
get away from in קדשים. Kodshim. Anyway, so דחוי dechuy is something
was fit to be used, it gets into a state where it's
not fit, it's considered pushed away and rejected, and once you're rejected,
it's like, don't try coming back. Like once a professor is passed
over
for tenure, it's like, you're not getting tenure. Okay, anyway, so this
blood, since it went to my left hand, let's use that example,
it was in a state when it was for that moment in
a state when it was not fit to be,
an עבודה avodah wasn't fit to be done with it. So that
should make it just rejected and now we can't go ahead and
do a redo. Okay. ולא הוי דחוי, Velo havay dechuy, why not
make it a דחוי? dechuy? So why isn't it a דחוי? dechuy?
אמר ליה רבינא לרב אשי, Amar lei Ravina le-Rav Ashi, הכא, hacha,
הא אמר רבי ירמיה מדיפתי משמיה דרבא, ha amar Rabbi Yirmiah mi-Difti
mishmeih de-Rava, he's what said in the name of רבא, Rava, המני
חנן המצרי היא, Hamani Chanan HaMitzri hi, this is חנן המצרי, Chanan
HaMitzri, חנן Chanan the Egyptian,
from Egypt, דלית ליה דחויין. deleis lei dechuyin. He doesn't, he rejects
this whole category of דחוי. dechuy. He says that even if something
is in a state where it can't be used, if the state
changes or the circumstances change, it can be reused. Okay.
How do you know that? דלית ליה דחויין. deleis lei dechuyin. דתניא,
Detanya, we've done a ברייתא, braita, חנן המצרי אומר אפילו דם בכוס
מביא חברו ומזווג לו. Chanan HaMitzri omer afilu dam bekos mevi chavero
u-mezaveg lo.
So this is what happens if you have to have the pair
of the goat on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, the goat that goes
לעזאזל L'Azazel and about the blood, the goat that you put the
blood in the inner sanctum there.
So what happens if both, if you lose one of those goats
and then you need to do a pairing again? So there's three
opinions as רש"י Rashi lays out about what happens if you lose
one of those
goats. So one opinion is if you lose one of those goats,
even if the other goat is alive, there's דחוי dechuy even by
live things. so the live goat that you have left, since for
a moment it can't be used because it doesn't have its pair,
that can't be used either and you need to bring two totally
new goats. That's דחוי בבעלי חיים. dechuy b'baalei chayim. There's another opinion
that says no, if something is alive you don't have דחוי, dechuy,
אין דחוי בבעלי
חיים, ein dechuy b'baalei chayim, but if the blood was—if the goat
was slaughtered, the, you know, for the inner חטאת chatas and you
caught the blood and then you lost the goat לעזאזל, l'azazel, then
you have to throw out the blood and start it all over
again because the blood was דחוי, dechuy, something that's inanimate can be
rejected and pushed away. And then you have חננא מצרי Chanana Mitzri
who says even in inanimate objects there's no דחוי. dechuy. Even if
you have the blood and the other one was lost, the blood
is not rejected, get another animal, pair it up with the blood
as it were, and then go ahead and continue using the blood.
Okay, so חננא מצרי Chanana Mitzri does not hold of דחוי dechuy
even by inanimate objects. Okay, אפילו דם בכוס, afilu dam b'kos, even
if the blood is in the—is already caught in the vessel, מביא
חברו ומזווג לו, mevi chaveiro u'mizaveig lo, you bring the parallel, you
know, goat and you and you pair it and you go on.
ורב אשי אמר, V'Rav Ashi amar, כל שבידו לא הוי דחוי. kol
she'biyado lo havi dechuy. רב אשי Rav Ashi says no, there's another
reason it's not דחוי. dechuy. Even if in general you hold of
דחוי, dechuy, something that could be trivially fixed—now he doesn't say trivially,
he says something that's in your power, but there's an element of
triviality—something that could be trivially fixed is not considered like it ever
got pushed off, right? It was just like oh, this is just
a slight problem, I fell on the ground, I'll pick it up,
you know. It's like it's not seen as getting into a state,
oh my God, it's in a state and it's unusable, now we
have to reverse the state. It's a—whatever, it's a technical—it's a little
problem, I'm going to fix it right away. There's nothing, you know.
So that never really gets the label of being pushed away. So
here, if it's in my left hand, I just go ahead and
put it back to my right hand. Now, the reason I say
trivial—so therefore that's never considered דחוי dechuy because it would be trivial
to just put it back into my right hand. Okay, the reason
I say trivial is because in the case of the goats, right,
or why don't you say even if you lose the goat, the
blood isn't—isn't דחוי dechuy because just get another goat? What's the big
deal? Just get another goat. That's בידו, b'yado, you can go go
bring another goat. So clearly it's not enough—but no, we do say
that in that case, the blood is considered rejected. So clearly בידו
b'yado is not sufficient. It has to essentially be trivially בידו, b'yado,
רש״י Rashi more or less says that. Okay, but כל שבידו, kol
she'biyado, anything that's like trivial and it's in your ability to fix,
it doesn't get into a state of דחוי. dechuy. כל שבידו לא
הוי דחוי. kol she'biyado lo havi dechuy. אמר רב אשיא, Amar Rav
Ashia, כוותיה דרב אשי מסתברא. k'vash'teih d'Rav Ashi mistabra. Like רב אשי
Rav Ashi makes sense. מאן שמעת ליה דאית ליה דחויים, man sham'at
lei d'is lei dechuyim, because who do we know holds of the
principle of דחוי? dechuy? רבי יהודה. Rebbi Yehuda. We know that there's
a רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda position who holds of the principle of
דחוי. dechuy. How do you know it? דתנן, d'tnan, ועוד אמר רבי
יהודה, v'od amar Rebbi Yehuda, נשפך הדם ימות המשתלח. nishpach hadam yamut
hamishtaleach. Okay, that if the blood gets spilled, you have to let
the לעזאזל l'azazel die—meaning you don't actively kill it, but anyway you
start the whole process again. So that's a דחוי dechuy even by
a בעל חי, baal chai, even the living לעזאזל l'azazel is pushed
away if its pair got lost. או מת המשתלח נשפך הדם. o
meit hamishtaleach nishpach hadam. Similarly, if the one that was לעזאזל l'azazel
died, the blood has to get thrown out and you do another
whole pair. So that's a more obvious case of דחוי dechuy by
something that's not a בעל חי. baal chai. But anyway, רבי יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, it's clear that he is of the position he holds
of דחוי, dechuy, even the—even the most broadest definition of דחוי, dechuy,
even by בעל חי. baal chai. And nevertheless, ושמעינן ליה דאמר כל
שבידו לא הוי דחוי. v'sham'inan lei d'amar kol she'biyado lo havi dechuy.
The same רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda who holds of דחוי, dechuy, I
can prove to you that he says that when it's in your
hand to fix it and it's trivial, it's not דחוי. dechuy. Where
do you see he says that? דתניא, d'tanya, we learned in a
ברייתא. braisa. רבי יהודה אומר, כוס אחד היה ממלא מדם התערובות Rebbi
Yehuda omer kos echad hayah memalei mi'dam hata'arovos. וזורקו בבת אחת כנגד
היסוד. That what they would do on פסח Pesach is they would
be שחט, shachting, you know, thousands, hundreds of thousands of sacrifices, the
place would be a madhouse. Inevitably, or there could be a concern
that some blood got spilled and some blood of some person's קרבן
korban wasn't put on the altar. So what רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says is I got the perfect fix. At the end of the
day, before the day is over, scoop up some of the blood
on the floor of the עזרה. azarah. Again, assuming that all the
bloods are equally commingled. In that, if there was any blood, any
that got spilled and didn't get put on the altar, in that
mixture will be some of that blood. And then you throw it
on the altar and boom, you fixed it. Okay, and by the
way, now you'll say but what do you mean, it's microscopic, that
blood of the kosher—of the—of the קרבן korban that needs to be
fixed. Well, רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda is of the position that אין
דם מבטל דם. ein dam m'vateil dam. Okay, that if it's all—if
it's all the same substance, it's all blood, it's—everything is considered present.
Okay, it doesn't—no particular blood loses its identity because there's no loss
of identity because it's all blood. So therefore רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
says here's a way to make sure that the blood that got
spilled, if there was blood that got spilled, is now being put
on the altar. Okay, so what—the point is that's all very nice,
but what about דחוי? dechuy? For the time that it was on
the ground, it was not—it was not in a position to be
put on the altar. So you see if it's able to fix,
it's considered to be not a problem. Okay, so not דחוי. dechuy.
So the גמרא Gemara says, שמע מינה מעלי לתיקון.
shma mina maali l'tikun.
What, yeah, exactly, that's מעלי לתיקון, maali l'tikun, good point. שמע מינה
כל שבידו לא הוי דחוי שמע מינה. shma mina kol she'biyado lo
havi dechuy shma mina. You see that if it's in your hand
it's not דחוי, dechuy, good point. גופא, gufa, now let's go back
and look at that actual debate now about קרבן פסח korban Pesach
or that position. דתניא, d'tanya, we learned in a ברייתא, braisa, רבי
יהודה אומר Rebbi Yehuda omer, כוס אחד היה ממלא מדם התערובות. Now
let's go back and look at that actual debate now about קרבן
פסח korban pesach or that position. תניא, tanya, we're talking about a
ברייתא. braita. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, כוס אחד היה מלא
מדם התערובות, kos echad haya malei midam hata'aruvot, ושאם ישפך אחד מהם,
v'she-im yishapach echad mehem, if one of them, if one of them
gets
spilled of the blood that never got put on the altar, נמצא
שהוא מכשירו, nimtza shehu machshiro, through this you'll make it kosher. אמרו
לו לרבי יהודה, Amru lo l'Rabbi Yehuda, they said to Rabbi Yehuda,
והלא לא נתקבל בכלי, v'halo lo nitkabel bikli, how do you know,
maybe the blood that got spilled on the ground that you're trying
to fix didn't get spilled from a כלי שרת, kli sharet, maybe
it went straight from the animal's neck onto the ground and therefore
this isn't going to fix it? Now of course the answer is
okay, but so I won't fix that case, but I'll fix the
case when it got in a כלי kli and it spilled. Like
I'm not promising you I'm going to fix every case, but I'll
fix the cases that can be fixed. So I never really understood
this question. Okay, but anyway that's what they said. Ha, how do
you know it's going to fix it? Maybe the problem is worse.
So
the
גמרא Gemara says, or so the ברייתא braita says, מנין יודע? minayin
yode'a? So the
גמרא Gemara says back, how do they know that it wasn't caught
in a כלי? kli? אלא שמא לא נתקבל בכלי, ela shema lo
nitkabel bikli, maybe it wasn't. Now again, okay, maybe it wasn't, but
maybe it was, at least I'm fixing something. So maybe it seems
that it's a problem, you know, that maybe the problem is not
just that you're not fixing it, but maybe there's an active problem
if you're throwing invalid blood on the altar. Okay, now we had
the whole question if you throw invalid blood on the altar, does
it make the rest שיריים shirayim or something? We never said that
there was some like איסור issur to do that, but somehow that's
the question they're asking him. Ah, maybe there's some real invalid blood
here that you can't fix. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר להן,
amar lahen, so the ברייתא braita continues, he said back to them,
top of ל"ה ע"א, lamed-heh amud aleph, אף אני
לא אמרתי אלא בנתקבל בכלי. af ani lo amarti ela benitkabel bikli.
No, I'm only talking about a case when it was caught in
a vessel and then spilled. So the גמרא Gemara says, והוא גופיה
מנין יודע? v'hu gufeih minayin yode'a? So how does he know that
was the case? What do you mean I'm only talking about the
case? Meaning, it's not like we wait to the end of the
day and get every כהן kohen to report if anybody ever had
a spill and then we're going to decide. What he's basically saying
is we do this as a standard operating procedure. At the end
of the day, since there's a likelihood that some blood got spilled
and this is going to be the fix. So again, I don't
understand why he has to say I'm only talking about that case.
And then the גמרא Gemara says, well how do you know that?
I don't know that. But what I mean is that's the case
it's going to fix. You do this as a standard operating procedure,
maybe there's some invalid blood it won't fix, but I'm doing it
for the case of the invalid blood that can be fixed, the
one that was caught in the vessel and then got spilled. So
I really don't really understand what this whole discussion is, but anyway.
For what it's worth, I'm translating it the way I was trying
to say is that maybe the blood that you're scooping back up
on the altar in the כלי kli that you're now trying to
fix never was on the, not that you're trying to fix blood
that never was on the floor, meaning but if you're just gathering
blood into a כלי kli that never ever got to the floor
to begin with, then it's not, then you can't throw it on
the מזבח mizbeach because it was blood that, so then he's saying
no no no I'm talking...
Right, so that's what I said. The only way that they, the
way to, it's not the question you're only gathering that blood, you're
gathering all the blood that has a mixture of all the bloods.
Okay, but the, so the only way to understand what the issue
is, is if there's an assumption that there's some איסור issur of
putting invalid blood on the מזבח. mizbeach. But let's also remember that
you're gathering a total תערובת. ta'aruvot. So there might be traces of
invalid blood. So we have to assume two things: we have to
assume that there's somehow a, you know, an איסור issur of throwing
invalid blood, and that איסור issur is even when there's, it's only
traces of it or whatever. That's the only way to explain the
debate, but I just don't know why we're taking that assumption. Anyway,
we continue. So the גמרא Gemara says, והוא גופיה מנין יודע? v'hu
gufeih minayin yode'a? How does he know this? דכהנים זריזים הם ועבדי
האי. d'kohanim zrizim hem v'avdi hai. That's an interesting word, האי, hai,
means fast, quickly. Because כהנים kohanim are, כהנים kohanim are careful. From
the one hand, because they're careful, we assume that they, all the
blood gets caught in a vessel. On the other hand, עבדי האי,
avdi hai, they act they're very very fast. Okay? ומשתפכין, umishtapchin, and
then it spills. So basically because the act of catching the blood,
we can assume that, you know, you have to wait when you
catch/stop to catch the blood. So that we can assume that they're
not going to let an animal be slaughtered without the blood get
caught. But then they're like very fast and if you're running and
very fast, then an accident can happen and some of the blood
and the blood could spill. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, ולא דם התמצית מעורב בו? v'lo dam hatamtzit me'urav bo?
But one minute says the גמרא, Gemara, you know, if you're picking
from all of the blood that got mixed up, you have some
blood that was not דם הנפש. dam hanefesh. You have some of
the blood that was just blood that came out after the life
force seemed to have left the animal, and that's not blood that
goes on the altar. So again, the presumption seems to be that
even though you're all doing it for a legitimate purpose and there's
a lot of kosher blood here whatever, that if there's some פסול
pasul blood, you don't want to be doing it. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says, ולא דם התמצית מעורב בו? v'lo dam hatamtzit me'urav
bo? רבי יהודה לטעמיה דאמר דם התמצית קרוי דם. Rabbi Yehuda l'ta'ameih
d'amar dam hatamtzit karuy dam. No, Rabbi Yehuda says that even the
non-life blood is considered blood and presumably therefore can go on the
altar. דתניא, d'tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, דם התמצית באזהרה.
dam hatamtzit b'azhara. רבי יהודה אומר בכרת. Rabbi Yehuda omer b'karet. דם
התמצית dam hatamtzit you get a negative prohibition but you don't get
כרת karet because on the one hand it's blood, on the other
hand it's the, when the תורה Torah says כרת, karet, it says
you know, it says כי נפש כל בשר דמו היא ki nefesh
kol basar damo hi etc., it emphasizes the blood of the soul.
So the point is this is blood but not soul blood, and
therefore you don't get כרת. karet. רבי יהודה אומר בכרת. Rabbi Yehuda
omer b'karet. Rabbi Yehuda says you get כרת, karet, so presumably he
thinks that either it is soul blood or he thinks that he
doesn't hold of the whole distinction and he treats all... blood the
same. So therefore, according to him, this blood could also go on
the altar, it's not a problem of putting invalid blood on the
altar. So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute, ואמר רבי אלעזר מודה
רבי יהודה לעניין כפרה שאינו מכפר. Ve’amar Rabbi Elazar modeh Rabbi Yehuda
le’inyan kapparah she’eino mechaper. It might be when it comes to the
prohibition of eating it he doesn't make draw that line, but when
it comes to what blood atones, there he agrees that you need
soul blood, שנאמר כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר, shene’emar ki hadam hu
banefesh yechaper, the blood of the soul atones. דם שהנפש יוצא בו
קרוי דם, דם שאין הנפש יוצא בו אינו קרוי דם. Dam shehanefesh
yotzei bo karui dam, dam she’ein hanefesh yotzei bo eino karui dam.
Now the point here should not be whether it's קרוי דם karui
dam because רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda’s whole point is that it is
called blood. Either way it's called blood, but that's just a stock
phrase of the גמרא. Gemara. רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda’s point is even
if it's called blood and even if you get כרת, Kares, clearly
you need דם הנפש dam hanefesh to be מכפר. mechaper. So we're
back to our question, which is again, we're having some assumption that
even though this fixes the issue, you shouldn't be throwing פסול pasul
blood on the מזבח. mizbe’ach. So before we had the question maybe
some of the blood on the floor was blood that never got
caught in a כלי, kli, so you'd be throwing a little bit
of פסול pasul blood on the מזבח. mizbe’ach. That's the only way
to explain the debate between רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and the חכמים.
Chachamim. And here the problem is some of the blood is not
the soul blood. And now because you're taking blood and you're throwing
it on the altar and it's a mixture, some of that is
not כשר kosher blood being put on the מזבח. mizbe’ach. So the
גמרא Gemara says,
אלא רבי יהודה לטעמיה דאמר אין דם מבטל דם. Ela Rabbi Yehuda
leta’amei de’amar ein dam mevattel dam. So now it seems different, right?
Now it seems that the גמרא Gemara is saying the problem wasn't
that the invalid blood was going on the altar, the problem was
that the invalid blood was negating, erasing the presence of the valid
blood that you needed to put on the altar. And it was
causing ביטול. bittul. And the answer is that there's no ביטול bittul
because blood and blood there's no ביטול. bittul. Of course if that's
true, it's not clear to me why the גמרא Gemara had to
ask about דם התמצית. dam hatamtzit. Why didn't the גמרא Gemara just
ask about about, you know, all the blood of all the כשר
kosher of that was put on the altar that there was still
spillage? I mean there's always going to be spillage even of blood
that eventually gets to the altar. So why didn't the גמרא Gemara
just say there's all these bloods here and they cause ביטול? bittul?
And the answer is there's no ביטול. bittul. Okay, so okay, יישר
כח, yasher koach, there's no ביטול. bittul. But what we still sort
of, like I'm saying, is unclear is how much is the גמרא
Gemara bothered by the idea that within this mixture that everything is
present, is it a problem that some of it is פסול pasul
or, you know, not a problem? That's the way to understand why
how the exchange before that they said, oh maybe some of it
never got to a כלי. kli. But anyway here we don't seem
to be bothered with it. Some of it is דם התמצית, dam
hatamtzit, fine, it doesn't cause ביטול. bittul. I got the good blood
and I'm going to put the... so since it has some of
the blood that needs to go on the altar, I go ahead
and I do what I was planning on doing. All right, anyway.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi
Yehuda, said רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
לדבריכם למה פוקקים העזרה? Ledivreichem lama pokekim ha’azarah? According to you, that
you don't feel that you should be gathering blood and throwing it
to solve this, why do we know that what they did on
ערב פסח Erev Pesach was they put a stopper, you know I
said that they had like this channel, you know, in the ground
that like with running water that like all of the stuff, you
know, all the blood that spilled or whatever, they would squeegee it
and it would all sort of go out. Okay, but on ערב
פסח Erev Pesach they put a stopper there. So imagine like you're
in Israel and you're trying to wash your floor on ערב שבת
Erev Shabbos you put the water, you know I love it, they
just throw the bucket of water, right, and the soap and they
don't have to whatever, but you do it but then you never
open up the drain. Okay, so you're walking around in soapy water.
So that's what they did here. You were walking around in blood.
So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, I know why I think they
did that on ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, so that you'd have all
the blood that would still be there and any blood that spilled
or whatever and, you know, and then you'd be able to do
my fix. But according to you that you're not... you don't do
my fix because you're afraid that there's I don't know what, either
you're afraid that there's ביטול bittul or you're afraid that the פסול
pasul blood there's blood there that can't be fixed and that shouldn't
be put on the altar, so why do they stop... why do
they put, you know, why do they stop up the drain? So
he says, לדבריכם למה פוקקים העזרה? Ledivreichem lama pokekim ha’azarah? So אמרו
לו, Amru lo, they said to him,
שבח הוא לבני אהרן שיהלכו עד ארכובותיהם בדם. Shevach hu livnei Aharon
sheyelechu ad arkuvoteihem bedam. Okay, right, שבח? shevach? Oh it's beautiful that
the כהנים Kohanim are walking around in a whole, in a few
inches of blood up to their ankles in blood, okay, during the
עבודת כהונה? avodat kehuna? Well
that's the next question of the גמרא. Gemara. Maybe it somehow that
it demonstrates I don't know how this is a שבח, shevach, maybe
somehow it demonstrates how much קרבנות korbanot are brought today. Certainly, I
the idea like I and בני ישראל, Bnei Yisrael, right?
Shouldn't that be בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael bring all these קרבנות?
korbanot?
Yeah, no, I know, I... I can't get it, it's like, you
know, it's like most people we think of animal sacrifices and like
a lot of people nowadays, right, there's this like instinctive like, you
know, visceral recoil, oh the slaughtering and this and that and that's
supposed to be a holy service. This is like no, embracing it.
Like somehow, you know, embracing the bloodiness of it somehow, that's like
what a sanctified עבודה. avodah. I can't get into that mindset, I
don't understand it. Yes.
Yeah, but anybody who eats meat, that's what happens in a slaughterhouse.
Yes, but you'd rather at least for our sensibilities, you want to
sort of be protected from that. You want to get your chicken
that's completely doesn't have any smell, doesn't have any whatever, nice and
wrapped, nice, no blood, right. Anyway, so this is a very opposite
sensitivity, sensibilities. Okay, anyway, so so okay,
יישר כח, yasher koach, that's their answer. But now the גמרא Gemara
says, ומיהו... Umihu... ומיהת הדם הוי חציצה? Umihate vadam havay hatzitza? Now
this is a question even if you are regardless of why you're
stopping up the blood. The reality is if they were walking around
in a few inches of blood, so what about the חציצה hatzitza
problem? The blood is getting between their feet and the floor. So
the גמרא Gemara says, לח ולא הוי חציצה. Lach velo havay hatzitza.
No,
a liquid isn't considered a חציצה, hatzitza, okay, because it's not like
a real barrier. You know, you push down on a liquid and
you know you can get to the floor. Okay, דתנן, detnan, הדם
והדיו והדבש, hadam vehadyo vehadvash, blood and ink and and honey, וחלב
vechalav and milk, יבשים חוצצים, yeveshim chotzitzim, if they're dried up, so
then they are חציצה. hatzitza. לחים אינם חוצצים, lachim einam chotzitzim, if
they're still moist, then that's not considered a חציצה. hatzitza. Now that's
not said about כהונה, kehuna, that's said about like going to the
מקוה, mikva, but anyway. והא קמיטנפי מאניהו? Veha kamitnafi manayhu?
Again, all these questions are not about Rabbi Yehuda and the רבנן.
Rabbanan. Once you're saying that's the reality, we have some problems to
solve. Okay, their בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, which went like down to
their like you know ankles, they're getting they're getting dirty. ותנן, vetnan,
היו בגדיו מטושטשים, hayu begadav metushtashim, if the garments were like you
know soiled, ועבד עבודתו פסולה, ve'avad avodato pesula, the עבודה avoda is
invalid. So how is this valid? וכי תימא דמדלו להו? vekhi teima
demadlo lehu? Maybe what they did is that they lifted it up,
you know, they sort of what do you call it, they hiked
up their you know the bottom of their
of the bottom? והתניא, vehatanya, מדו, mado, מדו בד כמדתו, mado bad
kemidato, שלא יחסר ושלא יותיר, shelo yechsar veshelo yotir, it has to
be exactly his his to
you know tailored to his height. Now you could say that's a
דין din in the בגד, beged, not the way it's worn, but
the גמרא Gemara elsewhere says it also has to be worn that
way. It has to be worn going down you know to his
ankles. So what are you going to do here? It's going to
invalidate. So the גמרא Gemara says, בהולכת איברים לכבש. beholachat evarim lakevesh.
Oh no no no, this they would only do this when they
would bring the limbs to the altar and therefore it wouldn't that's
not a real עבודה avoda and it wouldn't matter. Of course they
would only walk in the blood. So the גמרא Gemara says what
would they do the rest of the time? They would hover the
rest of like, what do you mean they would only walk in
the blood? If that's what's going on, that there's a three inches
of blood, they can't just determine when they're walking and what, so
the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that. Okay, דלאו עבודה
היא. delav avoda hi. Hello, are you telling me you don't need
to be wear בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna when you're doing the walking
of the limbs to the altar? והתניא, vehatanya, ויקריב הכהן את הכל
המזבחה, veyakriv hakohen et hakol hamizbecha, זו הולכת איברים לכבש. zo holachat
evarim lakevesh. Okay, that's bringing it to the ram to the ramp
and presumably it needs to be a כהן kohen and it needs
to be with בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna.
So that's not a thing that doesn't need it. אלא בהולכת עצים
למערכה דלאו עבודה היא. ela beholachat etzim lema'aracha delav avoda hi. Fine
fine fine, the only time they would walk around in the blood
and that we'd say oh it's beautiful, they're walking around with their
feet in the blood, look how wonderful this looks, that's when they
brought the wood to the altar, which doesn't really technically need a
כהן kohen or בגדי כהונה. bigdei kehuna. So the גמרא Gemara says,
okay, that's wonderful. So what are they doing all the rest of
the time? ולעבודה היכי אזלי? vela'avoda heichi azlei? How would they walk
for the עבודה? avoda? So the גמרא Gemara says, אזלי אאיצטבא. azlei
a'itztaba. There would be like these little platforms, not external, built into
the ground, raised raised platforms on the ground. You mean they were
always there? So yes, I don't know, what's it saying? It's saying
on ערב פסח, Erev Pesach, like you know when they're bringing all
the קרבנות, korbanot, everybody is standing I mean you understand like you
could build a not an external platform, you could build the ground
with raised sections, you know raised little things. So what it means,
they're standing on these raised things and they're שוחט-ing shochat and they're
catching and then they're jumping from one to the next? You know
I mean you know so it could be just there's a walkway
that goes in like fine, they're walking, but it's pretty funny. Now
we have a whole different scenario, right? You have a whole series
of raised platforms and all of this to allow them for when
they have to bring the wood to the altar to allow for
that one עבודה avoda for them to walk in blood because somehow
we're supposed to think that that's a beautiful thing. Like this makes
like no sense. I don't understand this. For רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
at least, it's a way of fixing the קרבן פסח. korban pesach.
Okay, yes.
Isn't the entire architecture of the עזרה Azara supposed to be as
specified?
Yeah, I don't know. I don't I don't really understand this. Okay,
moving on. משנה. Mishna. All right, that's the end of that discussion.
Let's take a look at the משנה. Mishna. השוחט את הזבח. hashochet
et hazevach.
Back to פיגול, pigul, never get away from פיגול. pigul. השוחט את
הזבח לאכול דבר שאין דרכו לאכול להקטיר דבר שאין דרכו להקטיר. hashochet
et hazevach le'echol davar she'ein darko le'echol lehaktir davar she'ein darko lehaktir.
So the previous discussion is what if a פסול pasul person has
these types of thoughts and that led us to our discussion. Okay,
now we say you slaughter the sacrifice to eat something that's not
normally eaten or להקטיר דבר שאין דרכו להקטיר, lehaktir davar she'ein darko
lehaktir, to burn something not normally burned. So it could be not
normally eaten because it's not edible, like physically it's like I don't
know the hoof, or it could be not normally eaten because it's
normally burned on the altar. Okay, and that's מחשבין מאכילת מזבח לאכילת
אדם. mechashvin me'achilat mizbe'ach le'achilat adam.
So in those cases, כשר, kasher, it's kosher. Okay, if if you're
thinking that you're going to eat the entrails or burn the meat
or something like that. רבי אליעזר פוסל. Rabbi Eliezer posel. Rabbi Eliezer
invalidates. Presumably he doesn't say it's פיגול, pigul, but he does invalidate.
So that's מחשבין mechashvin according to Rabbi Eliezer, מאכילת מזבח לאכילת אדם
ומאכילת אדם לאכילת מזבח. me'achilat mizbe'ach le'achilat adam ume'achilat adam le'achilat mizbe'ach.
Okay, רבי אליעזר פוסל. Rabbi Eliezer posel. לאכול דבר שדרכו לאכול להקטיר
דבר שדרכו להקטיר. le'echol davar shedarko le'echol lehaktir davar shedarko lehaktir.
Now your plan is to eat something normally edible. You're going to
eat the meat, but at the wrong time. Burn the you know
the entrails at the wrong time.
פחות מכזית. pachot mikezayit. You're only planning on doing it with less
than a כזית's kezayit worth. So some of this was implicit in
the early... Anyway כשר, kasher, the קרבן korban is still valid. That
doesn't make פיגול. pigul. לאכול כחצי זית להקטיר כחצי זית, leachol kechetzi
zayit lehakteer kechetzi zayit, let’s say it was a full זית zayit
made up of not two types of eating, you know, but of
an eating and a burning on the altar. I’m going to eat
half a כזית kezayit at the wrong time and burn a half
a כזית kezayit on the wrong time. So in that case,
כשר, kasher, the קרבן korban is still כשר, kasher, שאין אכילה והקטרה
מצטרפין. she’ein achila vehaktara mitztarfin. We, this is things we’ve seen before,
right? The eating and the act about burning it up on the
altar, those don’t combine. If I plan to eat a half a
כזית kezayit at the wrong time and a half a כזית kezayit
in the wrong place, that combines to invalidate, but an eating and
a burning on the altar does not combine to invalidate. שאין אכילה
והקטרה מצטרפין. she’ein achila vehaktara mitztarfin. השוחט את הזבח, Hashochet et hazevach,
to eat a כזית kezayit מן העור מן הרוטב מן הקיפה מן
האלל מן העצמות מן הגידים מן הקרניים מן הטלפיים. min ha’or min
harotav min hakipa min ha’alal min ha’atzamot min hagidim min hakarnayim min
hatelafim.
So now it’s we’re talking about a case of something that’s not
normally fit to be eaten, but not fit to be eaten for
a more simple reason, not because it’s normally burnt on the altar,
but because it’s just inedible. Inedible. Okay. So you have your thought
to eat any of these various things in the wrong time, but
they’re inedible, so you’re not going to invalidate the sacrifice. Okay. חוץ
לזמנו וחוץ למקומו כשר. Chutz lizmano vechutz limkomo kasher.
It’s כשר. kasher. Now so what are these things? So עור or
is of course the leather. רוטב rotav is weird. רוטב rotav is
like the gravy when you cook it, but like obviously that’s not
inedible, but that’s not the קרבן korban itself, that’s just the gravy.
Okay. ומן הקיפה. umin hakipa. קיפה kipa is also like goop at
the bottom of a pot. That’s, עור, or, רוטב, rotav, וקיפה vekipa
is something that sometimes comes up in other contexts. So, you know,
the עור, or, the רוטב, rotav, and the קיפה kipa is not
really directly relevant to this. Anyway, ומן האלל. umin ha’alal. האלל ha’alal
is like the, the sinew I think or the bone of the,
like in, yeah, the sinew in the neck, which is very tough
and not edible.
Where am I? I lost my place.
ומן העצמות, umin ha’atzamot, the bones.
Important discussion that gets around issues of gelatin or whatever, gets to
things like this about bones. Does it have marrow? Does it not
have marrow? ומן הגידים, umin hagidim, the general the sinews. ומן הקרניים,
umin hakarnayim, horns. ומן הטלפיים, umin hatelafim, the hooves. Okay. So any
of these things are inedible. חוץ לזמנו וחוץ למקומו כשר, Chutz lizmano
vechutz limkomo kasher, and כשר. kasher. ואין חייבים עליהם. ve’ein chayavim aleihem.
Now that’s, that it’s not considered enough of edible thing to make
it into פיגול. pigul. What about if your animal is פסול pasul
or טרפה, treifa, for example? This is why it’s relevant to gelatin.
And you eat these parts of a טרפה treifa animal, or you
eat these parts of an animal that’s פסול pasul for another reason.
The animal was left over and it became נותר, notar, right? It
was left over day and now it’s invalid for that reason. ואין
חייבים עליהם משום פיגול נותר וטמא. Ve’ein chayavim aleihem mishum pigul notar
vetamei. If the animal became נותר, notar, was left over, or the
animal became פיגול pigul because the, because the כהן kohen thought to
eat, to eat the meat in the wrong place, so the whole
animal becomes פיגול pigul when he plans to eat a כזית kezayit
in the wrong, I mean in the wrong time. Right? Or a
טמא tamei person touches it and it’s invalid, or you’re טמא tamei
or whatever and you can’t eat the קרבן korban when you’re טמא,
tamei, and you eat from the hooves and the horns and whatever,
you did not violate. They’re not meat, they’re not edible, they’re not
part of the קרבן. korban. Okay. And that’s why some of this
discussion, you know, is relevant to like the gelatin issue. Okay. Now,
השוחט את המוקדשין. Hashochet et hamukdashin. If you שחט shacht sanctified things.
רש״י Rashi says that whenever it says the word מוקדשים, mukdashim, it
actually means female animals. I don’t know why that’s true. I don’t
know what, anything implicit in the word, but the context always when
we say השוחט מוקדשין hashochet mukdashin is then we’re going to talk
about something that’s unique to it being female. Okay. So you slaughter
these sanctified female animals
לאכול שליל ושליה בחוץ, leachol shalil v'shilya bachutz, and your plan is
not to eat the meat and the wrong time or the wrong
place, but to eat the fetus or the or the placenta. Now
there’s a question, a whole difficulty about trying to get to the
bottom of exactly what the גמרא Gemara thinks the שליל shalil and
the שליה shilya is. For anyway, for our purposes we’re just going
to translate it as fetus and placenta. Okay. How do they translate
it in the English?
Fetus and placenta.
Fetus and placenta but and afterbirth which is the placenta. But I’m
just telling you like the whole placenta, is it really what the
placenta is? Because there’s other places that it makes it sound like
the placenta becomes the fetus or whatever. Anyway, but we’ll just translate
it that way. Anyway, so that’s your plan. לא פיגל. Lo pigel.
So it’s interesting, it should have said חוץ לזמנו, chutz lizmano, but
okay, because we’re talking about פיגול. pigul. But anyway, you don’t make
it פיגול pigul if your plan is to eat that. Now why
not? So presumably that’s edible. The fetus is edible. It’s not because
it’s inedible, but presumably it’s because it’s not considered to be physically
part of the sacrifice. This is a question about עובר ירך אמו,
ubar yerech imo, you know, which to some degree, I mean עובר
ירך אמו ubar yerech imo is used by some פוסקים poskim in
the whole abortion discussion, right, which ties directly into the, you know,
contemporary discourse. It’s my body, I get to decide what to do
with my body. No, it’s a separate living being and so on.
How much do you see the fetus as just part of the
mother, as a limb of the mother or not? So anyway, but
where it’s more used in the גמרא Gemara is not around questions
of abortion, I mean, it’s more used in the גמרא Gemara for
sort of more technical קרבן korban types of issues and things such
as this, okay, which is the animal becomes פיגול pigul if you
thought about eating a כזית kezayit of the meat in the wrong
place, right? Your thought was, oh excuse me, there’s two scenarios. One
is your thought is about the fetus and the other is your
thought is about
the
meat. presumably although this is what the גמרא Gemara's going to challenge
in the first line or raise in the first line, if my
plan was to eat a כזית Kaza'is of the קרבן Korban in
the wrong place, I also the fetus wouldn't be פיגול. Pigul. Presumably
the point is is that the fetus is not considered to be
one unit with the mother. So a thought about the fetus does
not make the mother into פיגול. Pigul. A thought about the mother
does not make the fetus into פיגול Pigul presumably. They're considered to
be two entities, okay? That's at least presumably. We'll see what we
get in the גמרא. Gemara.
Okay, so now, החושב לאכול מן העובר חוץ לא פיגל. Ha'chochev le'echol
min ha'ubar chutz lo pigel. המהלק את התורין לאכול ביציהם בחוץ לא
פיגל. Ha'molek es ha'torin le'echol beitzayam be'chutz lo pigel.
Now it's pretty clear that that's what's going on in the משנה
Mishnah about one entity because here it talks about eggs, okay? So
you שחט Shecht the turtledoves to eat their eggs. Now what do
we mean their eggs? The eggs that they left behind in the
nest? Presumably it means that the eggs that you might find inside
of the mother. Anyway, so that also, you plan to eat the
eggs inside the mother doesn't make the mother into a פיגול Pigul
because presumably it's a separate entity.
חלב המוקדשים
וביצי תורין אין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול ונותר וטמא. Chalav ha'mukdashim ve'beitzey
torin ein chayavin aleihem mishum Pigul ve'nosar ve'tamei.
So
if you actually made the mother פיגול, Pigul, planned to eat
a כזית Kaza'is of the animal in the wrong place in the
wrong time and then you and so now you're חייב Chayav on
all edible parts of the animal, you're not חייב Chayav if you
eat the milk of the animal. So one case is your thoughts
about the fetus and about the eggs don't make the
mother פיגול. Pigul. Now you have the thought about the mother and
you're going to now eat the milk or the eggs. So the
mother is פיגול, Pigul, but the milk or the eggs are not
פיגול. Pigul. Those are separate. Of course what's missing from the end
of this משנה Mishnah is the case of the fetus. So we
know a thought about the fetus doesn't make the mother פיגול, Pigul,
but by silence one gets the idea that a thought about the
mother could make the fetus פיגול, Pigul, and that's what we're going
to explore immediately in the גמרא. Gemara. And similarly even if the
thing became was left over and נותר Nosar and טמא Tamei whatever,
these things are either not meat, they're certainly not meat, and or
they're also not part of the mother. Okay, but you get it?
But what we have here is, so we've got, all right I
should have left my lovely picture of my cow, okay, we've got
a mother here and here's the fetus inside, okay, here's a little
baby fetus, whatever, looks like a person. Anyway, okay I guess we'll
have a little baby cow. Anyway, and that's so now so the
it says if you have a thought about this, here's your thought
bubble, here's the כהן, Kohen, okay, you have a thought about this,
the mother doesn't become פיגול. Pigul. Okay, what it doesn't say is
if you have a thought about the mother does this become פיגול.
Pigul. Logically you would say if this way it doesn't become פיגול,
Pigul, the other way it shouldn't be פיגול. Pigul. It's a separate
entity. But the end of it said the case that if you
have a thought about the mother
the end case of the משנה Mishnah was that if you have
a thought about the mother it says what doesn't become פיגול? Pigul?
It says the milk, right, doesn't become פיגול, Pigul, okay here's your
bucket of milk, okay, the milk doesn't become פיגול. Pigul. So the
but but it never said what the story would be about the
fetus. All right? So the משנה Mishnah says if you have a
thought about the fetus the mother doesn't, if you have a thought
about the mother the milk doesn't become פיגול. Pigul. Okay, what about
the does the fetus become פיגול? Pigul? So that's exactly is it
possible to be some asymmetry here and why would there be asymmetry?
If it's not part of the mother it's not part of the
mother. So that's what we're going to see as soon now as
we turn to the גמרא, Gemara, yes.
So the milk and the eggs are not פיגול Pigul or נותר
Nosar or טמא, Tamei, but are they מותר? Mutar?
Are
they חולין? Chullin?
They're not part of the sacrifice of the קרבן, Korban, what are
they?
Right, that's a good question.
Like right does it still get, I
mean because the milk is still something that's produced by something that's
sanctified. If I sanctify a tree, the fruit that goes afterwards, right,
although there it's קדושת בדק הבית Kedushas Bedek Ha'bayis and קדושת מזבח.
Kedushas Mizbayach. I mean no, I assume that it's still owned by
the בית המקדש, Beis Ha'mikdash, but it's just doesn't have like קדושת
קרבן, Kedushas Korban, but if it's produced by a קרבן, Korban, חלב
המוקדשים Chalav ha'mukdashim and by פסולי מוקדשים. Psulei mukdashim.
Right, yeah, if an animal that's been
sacrificed has been sanctified and it was at the בית המקדש. Beis
Ha'mikdash. Right, yeah, no I get it, no you're right, you're right.
No no if it was a case of בדק הבית Bedek Ha'bayis
there'd be no question that this would be straight, well that's the
whole question about how do we גידולי הקדש Gidulei Hekdesh is a
debate in the גמרא, Gemara, but that's גידולי הקדש Gidulei Hekdesh by
בדק הבית, Bedek Ha'bayis, this is essentially גידולי הקדש, Gidulei Hekdesh, you
know, by a... by קדשי מזבח. kodshei mizbeach. I'd have to check.
Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Reb Elazar, פיגול בזבח, pigul b'zevoach, נתפגל שליל.
nitpagel shalil. ובשליל u'vishalil לא נתפגל זבח. lo nitpagel zevoach. So he
basically says explicitly what was implicit by silence in the משנה. Mishnah.
Okay, if you have a פיגול pigul thought about the mother, actually
the fetus does become forbidden. If you have a פיגול pigul thought
about the fetus, the mother does not become forbidden. Now, what is
the הלכה halakha about that?
So the way רש״י Rashi explains this is רש״י Rashi says it
has to do with how edible the fetus is considered to be.
The fetus like, רש״י Rashi doesn't use this term, but basically we
have a category like in הלכה halakha called like נאכל על ידי
הדחק. ne'echal al yedei hadechak. Things are eaten in cases
of difficult circumstances you would eat it but not under normal circumstances.
Okay, so what רש״י Rashi says is the following: is in order
to make the animal פיגול, pigul, your thought has to be about
something that is normally eaten. So a thought about the fetus, it's
not about being one unit with the mother. The thought about the
fetus does not make the mother פיגול pigul because it's a thought
about something that's not normally eaten. But once you've made the mother
פיגול, pigul, then anything that is somewhat edible becomes forbidden. Okay, so
you need something a little more normal in order to make it
forbidden, but once it's forbidden, all parts of the animal that are
even somewhat edible are forbidden. That's the way רש״י Rashi reads it.
It's a how edible is it? The next two cases though there's
going to also be cases of asymmetry and there's going to be
an easier explanation for the asymmetry. So let's take a look. Okay,
now,
פיגול באלל, pigul b'alal, נתפגלה מוראה. nitpaglah mora. So now you're dealing
here with a bird and by a bird the neck muscle actually
is considered edible. So you have a plan of פיגול pigul for
the neck muscle of a bird. So now even the מוראה, mora,
even like the stomach where stuff gets digested and whatever, even that
becomes פיגול. pigul. Okay, so that's like you had a פיגול pigul
thought for the animal, even this thing about the stomach or whatever
becomes פיגול. pigul. But במוראה, bimora, if your thought was about the
stomach, okay, לא נתפגלה אלל, lo nitpaglah alal, the rest of the
bird does not become פיגול. pigul. Now, why not? So רש״י Rashi
gives his old answer: the stomach is like נאכל על ידי הדחק,
ne'echal al yedei hadechak, right? So therefore if the bird becomes פיגול,
pigul, then anything that's somewhat edible also becomes פיגול. pigul. But because
it's not normally eaten, it doesn't have enough to make
that to be of the source of the פיגול pigul of the
bird. Okay, so that's why רש״י Rashi explains it. It's like נאכל
על ידי הדחק. ne'echal al yedei hadechak. It can become פיגול pigul
but can't make פיגול. pigul. תוספות Tosafot has a much cleaner explanation.
The only problem is that it doesn't work well for the שליל,
shalil, for the case of the fetus, but it works for this
case and the next case, which is תוספות: Tosafot: it's not about
whether physically it's edible. It's about what does the הלכה halakha say
you're supposed to do with it? Okay, פיגול pigul thoughts only work
on parts of the animal that the תורה Torah says, the הלכה
halakha says you're supposed to eat or burn. Okay, or put on
the altar.
The מוראה, mora, the sort of crop of the gizzard or the
crop of the bird, the stomach of the bird, the תורה Torah
never tells you to eat it and never tells you to burn
it. What you normally do with this crop of the bird is
you basically toss it. So because it under even when the animal
is done properly is not part of the eating or the burning
of the altar, it's part of the discarded parts of the altar,
therefore a פיגול pigul thought about it is not relevant. Okay, so
that's why תוספות Tosafot says. A פיגול pigul thought about a part
of the animal that was never commanded to be eaten or burnt
is not a פיגול pigul thought. But if you made the animal
פיגול, pigul, then it applies to any edible part and this is
considered at least a somewhat edible part. Okay similarly,
and the next case makes תוספות's Tosafot scenario even clearer. Okay, פיגול
באימורין, pigul b'imurin, נתפגלה פרי. nitpaglah paree. Now since it says פרי,
paree, right? Why does it say פרי? paree? Why doesn't it say
קרבנות? korbanos? Because it's a shorthand for saying we're talking about the
פרים הנשרפים. parim hanisrafim. Certain animals, right, like on יום כיפור's Yom
Kippur an example, the blood was put in the inner sanctum and
you burnt the entrails on the altar. What did you do with
the meat of the animals of a חטאת chatas that the blood
goes on the inner sanctum? Anybody know? You burnt it outside the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay,
so the meat is not edible. Now רש״י Rashi would say not
edible because it's supposed to be burnt. So that's sort of רש״י-like
Rashi his not really edible category. But תוספות Tosafot says it's not
because it's edible or not edible. It's because this meat according to
the תורה Torah law is not supposed to be put on the
altar and is not supposed to be eaten. So you can't have
a פיגול pigul thought about the meat. The פיגול pigul thought is
that you're misdirecting it. Something that was supposed to be eaten and
supposed to be burnt on the altar specifically, burnt on the altar,
you're misdirecting. This is something that was neither supposed to be eaten
nor supposed to be burnt on the altar, so a פיגול pigul
thought about the meat. is not a problem. It's not a misdirecting
of it. Okay, clear? But a פיגול pigul thought about the אימורים,
emurim, which is misdirecting, makes all edible parts פיגול pigul and the
meat is physically speaking edible. That's the way תוספות Tosafos has it.
For תוספות Tosafos the issue is it doesn't work again for the
fetus, but the base, the simpler issue is a פיגול pigul thought
has to misdirect something that is headed to the altar or to
human consumption and therefore it does not apply to these things. So
פיגול באימורים נתפגלו הפרים, pigul be'emurim nitpaglu haparim, if your פיגול pigul
thought was about the entrails and then the meat is פיגול pigul
even though the תורה Torah says burn it, if you ate it,
you would be חייב chayav for פיגול. pigul. Okay, but פיגול בפרים
לא נתפגלו אימורים, pigul beparim lo nitpaglu emurim, if your thought was
about the meat that's supposed to be burnt outside, that doesn't create
פיגול pigul because that's not misdirecting something heading to the altars or
to a human. Okay, לימא מסייע ליה. leima mesayei lei. Now that's,
so that's his interesting examples of asymmetry. So now the גמרא Gemara
is going to see if that's true or not. Let's see if
I can prove this.
Is that true about all חטאת chatas offerings or just this?
No, just the ones where the blood is in the inner sanctum.
A normal חטאת chatas offering, the blood is, the meat is eaten
by the כהנים. kohanim. Right. Okay. Now לימא מסייע ליה. leima mesayei
lei. Let me try to support this. ושוין שהמחשב באכילת פרים ובשרפתן
לא עשה ולא כלום. veshavin she'hamachashev be'achilas parim uvesereifasan lo asa velo
klum. So there's a debate of רב שמעון Rav Shimon and the
חכמים Chachamim
about whether there's פיגול pigul by
פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim
because רב שמעון Rav Shimon says anything that the blood is not
put on the outer altar, you don't have פיגול. pigul. So רב
שמעון Rav Shimon categorically rejects פיגול pigul by פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim
because the blood is put on the inner altar. But even though
the חכמים Chachamim basically hold of פיגול pigul by פרים הנשרפים, parim
hanisrafim, they agree that the following cases are not פיגול. pigul. ושוין,
veshavin, they agree שאם חשב באכילת פרים ובשרפתן לא עשה ולא כלום.
she'im chashav be'achilas parim uvesereifasan lo asa velo klum. If you had
a plan regarding you're going to burn it in a different place
or burn it at a different time or what are you going
to do with the meat of the sacrifice, you didn't accomplish anything.
So this really makes תוספות'ס Tosafos's point, right? This המחשב, hamachashev, you
know why you didn't make the animal פיגול? pigul? Because it's about
something, it's about meat that's not about stuff on the altar and
it's not about stuff you're supposed to be eating. It's about the
meat that you're supposed to burn outside of the temple. So that's
not relevant to the world of פיגול. pigul. So you got it?
So if your thought had to do that you're going to eat
the meat that's supposed to be burnt outside of the temple or
you're going to burn it in the wrong time or wrong place,
whatever, that is not פיגול pigul because that's not about a part
of the sacrifice that is intended to be burnt on the altar
or that's intended to be eaten by human consumption. לא עשה ולא
כלום. lo asa velo klum. Now מאי לאו, mai lav, fine, so
that gets us that point. Now what it doesn't address is what
happens when you have a פיגול pigul thought about the entrails? Okay,
'cause if you have a פיגול pigul thought, presumably the חכמים Chachamim
say there is פיגול, pigul, I mean not presumably, they do say
there's פיגול pigul by פרים הנשרפים. parim hanisrafim. So where does the
פיגול pigul by פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim take place? It's not about
eating the meat because that's not relevant. So the only פיגול pigul
by the פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim could be if it's about the
entrails. So presumably says the גמרא, Gemara, if you had a thought
about the entrails, מאי לאו הכי קאמר באימורים נתפגלו הפרים. mai lav
hachi ka'amar be'emurim nitpaglu haparim. Now the meat becomes פיגול, pigul, so
that's exactly your proof of this asymmetry. So the גמרא Gemara says
לא, lo, not necessarily. הכי קאמר באימורים נתפגלו אימורים עצמן. hachi ka'amar
be'emurim nitpaglu emurim atzman. Maybe it is symmetrical. Maybe because a פיגול
pigul thought doesn't work on the meat, the meat doesn't become פיגול.
pigul. So then where do you get פיגול pigul by פרים הנשרפים?
parim hanisrafim? If you have a פיגול pigul thought on the entrails,
then the entrails become פיגול. pigul. Okay, and even though the entrails
are stuff that's supposed to be burnt, if you ate them, you'd
be חייב כרת. chayav kares. Okay, which is funny because normally פיגול
pigul speaks about like there's two parts, a מתיר matir and whatever,
anyway, but that's the point. We all agree to the principle that
a thought about eating the meat that's supposed to be destroyed outside
the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash is not a פיגול pigul thought. פיגול
pigul thought has to be misdirecting something that's supposed to be on
the altar or human consumption. So that's not a פיגול pigul thought,
we all agree that that does not make the animal פיגול. pigul.
The question is because that meat is excluded from פיגול pigul thoughts,
what's the story when the animal does become פיגול? pigul? Does is
the meat also similarly excluded and there's a symmetry? Or do we
say no, once the animal became פיגול, pigul, the meat also became
פיגול pigul with the animal? Yes.
So these entrails are burned on the altar,
although we normally would not eat them, they're treating them as if
they could be eaten?
Right, I mean they're physically able to be eaten and if you
did, you'd transgress פיגול pigul although you'd violate other things 'cause they're
supposed to be on the altar, right. Correct. Okay, so now we're
now we're going to continue to try to prove it. תא שמע,
ta shema, come and hear. פרים הנשרפים ושעירים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim use'irim
hanisrafim מועלין mo'alin בהן bahen משהוקדשו. mishe'hukdashu. So you have these פרים
הנשרפים parim hanisrafim that we're talking about, things that are going to
be, the blood is going to be in the inner sanctum and
the meat is going to be burnt outside the temple. So מעילה
me'ila begins from the time that you sanctified them. Now נשחטו, nishchetu,
now you slaughtered them, הוכשרו ליפסל בטבול יום ובמחוסר כפורים ובלינה. huchsharu
lehipasel bitvul yom uvimechusar kippurim uvelina. Now because they're meat, you slaughtered
them, now Now they can become פסול pasul if a טמא tamei
person touches them, a טבול יום, tevul yom, somebody who went to
the מקווה mikvah that day even, even only residual טומאה, tumah, somebody
who hasn't brought a sacrifice so they're still not totally טהור. tahor.
Anyway, now it's meat, so it can become טמא tamei ובלנה. uvelina.
The key that we're focusing on is, and now of course, no
big surprise, if you let the meat stay overnight, then it becomes
פסול pasul because it's נותר. nosar. That's what לינה lina is, it
slept over the night. No big surprises there, but the גמרא Gemara
now is going to make an interesting jump. If the meat can
become פסול pasul when it actually, this is the meat though, when
it's supposed to be burnt outside the temple. So what does it
mean that it's פסול בלינה? pasul belina? It means that if you
leave it overnight, it becomes נותר nosar and if I eat it,
I'm חייב chayav for נותר. nosar. So meat that actually stayed over
too long, even though it's not meat that normally is eaten, it's
meat that's burnt outside the temple, the laws of נותר nosar apply.
And now the גמרא Gemara is going to make a fascinating jump
between the world of thought and the world of action. It's like
we're kabbalists, right, עולם המחשבה olam hamachshava anyway the world of עשייה,
asiya, the world of, anyway, the world of thought and the world
of action because so much of פיגול pigul is because you're planning
on doing it, it's like you already did it. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara is going to say if this meat of פרים הנשרפים,
parim hanisrafim, the laws of נותר nosar can apply,
then why presumably the laws of פיגול pigul of plans of the
wrong time should apply as well. Okay? And this is to prove
that if you have a פיגול pigul thought about the entrails of
פרים הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, the meat becomes פיגול, pigul, the same way
the meat of פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim can be נותר, nosar, the
meat can become פיגול. pigul. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי לאו לינת בשר, mai lav linat basar, presumably it means that
the meat becomes נותר, nosar, okay, of פרים הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, even
meat that normally is
burned. ושמע מינה מיגו דפסלה בלינה פסלה במחשבה. ushma mina migo depasla
belina pasla bemachshava. Since the meat can become נותר, nosar, the meat
can become פיגול, pigul, because פיגול pigul is like it was all
done in the wrong time. So therefore the effect is פיגול pigul
is turning the thought of wrong time into somewhat of the reality
of wrong time. So if the meat can become נותר, nosar, the
meat can become פיגול. pigul. So that proves the asymmetry. A thought
about the meat doesn't make the animal פיגול, pigul, again a פרים
הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, but a thought about the אימורים imurim would make
the meat פיגול. pigul. The גמרא Gemara says, לא לינת אימורים. lo
linat imurim. No, maybe it means that only, we're not denying this
jump between thought and action, but maybe when we say that the
animal פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim can become נותר, nosar, what we mean
is that the entrails can become נותר. nosar. Maybe the meat that
is supposed to be burnt outside the temple never gets a status
of
נותר. nosar. לא לינת אימורים הוא. lo linat imurim hu. והא מדקתני
סיפא, veha midekatni seifa, one minute, but the end of
that ברייתא braita teaches,
כולן מועלין בהן על בית הדשן עד שיוצת הבשר. kulan moalin bahen
al beit hadeshen ad sheyutzat habasar. All of these things מעילה me'ila
continues to apply even after you're burning it, the meat, until the
meat like completely chars, okay, completely dissolves. Okay, so therefore the end,
we're talking about where are the problems lie, we're talking about the
meat, because we're talking about the מעילה me'ila applies to the meat
until the meat totally dissolves when it's being burned. So מכלל דרישא
לינת בשר. michlal deresha linat basar. So since the end we're talking
about the meat, earlier when we spoke about נותר nosar by these
animals, presumably we're also talking about the meat. Gemara says, מידי איריא?
midi irya? What type of proof is that? הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא.
ha kide'ita veha kide'ita. Each one is in its context. רישא אימורים,
resha imurim, in the beginning when we're talking about that the פרים
הנשרפים parim hanisrafim become נותר, nosar, we're talking about the entrails. וסיפא
בשר, veseifa basar, and there we're talking about the meat. So again,
that's a pretty big
push, it's like דחוק, dachuk, you know, that's a pretty difficult reading.
But anyway, that's what the גמרא Gemara says. Certainly the פשט pshat
of it is that the meat does become נותר. nosar. But to
me what's more surprising is the גמרא Gemara just takes for granted
this jump from the world of thought to the world of action,
that if the meat can become נותר, nosar, obviously the meat can
become פיגול. pigul. Okay, so again by פרים הנשרפים parim hanisrafim we
know that a thought about the meat doesn't make the animal פיגול
pigul because the meat is supposed to be burnt outside the temple.
The question is, can the meat become פיגול? pigul? Do you have
this asymmetry? Okay, and whoever it was, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar said
you did, and it seems to be proven here, and let's keep
on going. Okay, מתיב רבה, metiv Rabbah, Rabbah asks.
ואלו שאין מפגלין, ve'elu she'ein mefaglin, the following things, here's another ברייתא,
braita, that do not
מפגלין, mefaglin, do not make the animal פיגול. pigul. ואין מתפגלין, ve'ein
mitpaglin, they themselves don't become פיגול. pigul. Okay, what is it? צמר
שבראשי כבשים, tzemer sheberoshei kvasim, the hair at the, on the head
of the sheep. So even though you burn the sheep with its
skin, you don't burn the hair on the head. So therefore a
thought about burning the hair on the head at a wrong time
is not a misdirecting, because the hair is never supposed to be
burned. And it also doesn't become פיגול pigul because it's not edible.
Okay, so these are not things that are normally burned or eaten,
therefore they don't make פיגול pigul and because they're not edible they
don't become
פיגול. pigul. ושיער שבזקן התיישים, vese'ar shebezakan hatyashim, and the hair of
the beard of the goats. והעור והרוטב והקיפה והאלל. veha'or veharotev vehakipa
veha'alal. This is like our משנה, mishnah, the skin and the broth
and the jelly and the sediment. Skin and again עור or and
רוטב rotav and קיפה kippa is not so relevant. Anyway, the sinew
in the neck that's not edible, והמוראה vehamora'ah the crop, והעצמות v'hatzamot
of a bird, anyway והעצמות v'hatzamot the bones, והגידים v'hagidim and the
sinews, והקרניים v'hakarnayim the horns, והטלפיים v'hatalpayim and the hoofs, והשלב והשליא
והשליא, v'hashalav v'hashilya v'hashilya, there's those, okay, the fetus and the embryo
and that's the same thing, the fetus and the placenta, וחלב המוקדשים
v'chalav hamuktashim and the milk, וביצי תורים v'beitzay torim and the eggs.
So the milk and the eggs are edible but they're not part
of the animal. Okay? And this we don't know what this holds
about the
fetus. The easiest read about this is it holds that the fetus
is edible. It's like the milk and the eggs, okay, and therefore
it but but it's a separate entity. And because it's a separate
entity, it doesn't make the mother פיגול pigul and the mother doesn't
make it פיגול. pigul. כולן לא מפגלין ולא מתפגלין, kullan lo mifaglin
v'lo mitpaglin, all of these do not make the mother פיגול pigul
and do not become פיגול, pigul, ואין חייבין עליהם משום פיגול נותר
וטמא. v'ein chayavin aleihem mishum pigul notar v'tamay. Okay, now פיגול pigul
is a little redundant. If the mother became פיגול pigul or the
animal became פיגול, pigul, you're not חייב chayav for eating the hoofs
or whatever, not even חייב chayav for eating the milk or the
egg or the fetus. Okay, that's because again it's a separate entity.
Okay, either it's inedible or separate entity. Also though if the animal
was left overnight or the animal or you're טמא, tamay, you're also
not חייב chayav for eating these things. Okay, so that's interesting. You
שחטed shacht the mother, you left so again why you're לא חייב
lo chayav for eating the next morning you left it overnight the
hoofs is because that's inedible. But why am I not חייב chayav
for eating the next morning the fetus? And the answer is because
the only thing that's considered to be the קרבן korban is the
mother. The fetus is not considered to be the קרבן. korban. It's
seen as a separate entity, it's seen just like as the
milk that's in the udder. And therefore, okay, even if the whole
קרבן korban was left overnight and all the meat became טמא tamay
and the fetus is meat, I'm not חייב chayav for eating the
fetus because the fetus is not part of the קרבן. korban. Okay,
so it's not מפגל, mifagel, it doesn't make the mother פיגול, pigul,
it doesn't become פיגול, pigul, it's a separate entity. And similarly, if
the whole animal became נותר notar or טמא tamay whatever, it doesn't
apply to this thing. All right, so anyway, so it says like
this.
והמעלה מהן בחוץ פטור. v'hama'aleh meihen bachutz patur. Now if you brought
them outside of the temple, you are פטור patur because these are
not normally things that are offered up in the temple. That's why.
Now מאי לאו? mai lav? Okay, לא מפגלין את הזבח ולא מתפגלין
מחמת זבח. lo mifaglin et hazevach v'lo mitpaglin machmat zevach. So clearly
what it seems to be saying here is, I mean this is
totally פשט, pshat, they don't make the זבח zevach פיגול pigul and
they don't become פיגול pigul when the mother does. Okay, so this
would actually prove the opposite of רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer statement because
remember רבי אליעזר's Rebbi Eliezer statement was also about the fetus and
רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer had this asymmetry: the fetus doesn't make the
mother פיגול pigul but the mother makes the fetus פיגול. pigul. This
ברייתא braita seems to say explicitly not that way. It deals with
a case of the fetus but it fills in what wasn't said
in the משנה. mishna. And it says that in the case of
the fetus it both doesn't make the mother פיגול pigul and the
mother doesn't make it פיגול. pigul. So that's against רבי אליעזר. Rebbi
Eliezer. רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer held of an asymmetry. So the גמרא
Gemara says לא. lo. ולא מתפגל? v'lo mitpagel? No, says the גמרא,
Gemara, no, that's not necessarily what it means. It means לא מפגלין
את הזבח ולא מתפגלין מחמת עצמן. lo mifaglin et hazevach v'lo mitpaglin
machmat atzman. No, it means they don't make the mother פיגול pigul
and again if your thought was about the fetus it both doesn't
make the mother פיגול pigul and it doesn't make itself פיגול. pigul.
But all it's excluding is when your thought is about this thing.
It's not dealing with a case when your thought is about the
main animal. If your thought is about the hoofs, it doesn't make
the animal פיגול pigul and the hoofs aren't פיגול. pigul. If your
thought is about the horns, the horns it doesn't make the animal
פיגול pigul and the horns aren't פיגול. pigul. If your thought is
about the fetus, it doesn't make the animal פיגול pigul and it
doesn't make the fetus פיגול. pigul. So it's reading this as that
all the cases are when your thoughts are about just this object.
And it's saying that doesn't make the rest of the animal and
it doesn't even make the object itself. And it's not dealing with
the scenario when your thought is about the animal. And אינך הכי
נמי einach hachi nami רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer would say if your
thought is about the animal the fetus would become a problem. That's
what רבי אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer would say. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute אי הכי ei hachi if that's true
הא דקתני סיפא ha d'katani seifa that's what we taught at the
end כולן לא מפגלין ולא מתפגלין kullan lo mifaglin v'lo mitpaglin it
repeats itself. It says the following don't make פיגול pigul don't become
and then it repeats all of these things don't make and don't
become. הא תו למה לי? ha tu lama li? Why is it
repeating? It must be repeating to emphasize a broader read of the
scenarios that we're not just talking about thinking about the fetus. We're
also talking about thinking about the mother that the fetus doesn't become
פיגול. pigul. The גמרא Gemara says הא תו למה לי? ha tu
lama li? לטעמיה l'ta'ameh says the גמרא, Gemara, לדתניא lidtanya אין חייבין
עליו משום פיגול. ein chayavin alav mishum pigul. הא תו למה לי?
ha tu lama li? There's a it's redundant three times because it
says now it says and doesn't you're not חייב chayav for פיגול.
pigul. So obviously there's a lot of redundancy, throwaway phrases in this
ברייתא, braita, don't prove to me anything from that. אלא איידי דבעי
למתני נותר וטמא ela aidi d'ba'ei l'mitni notar v'tamay because it wanted
to say added the point that it doesn't also become נותר notar
and טמא. tamay. So it said the trio, there's like a חרש
שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan trio, there's a פיגול נותר טמא pigul
notar tamay trio. Because it wanted to say נותר וטמא, notar vetamei,
it was redundant and threw in the words they don't become פיגול.
pigul. תנא פיגול. tana pigul. So therefore there's throwaway phrases here. הכא
נמי, hacha nami, איידי דבעי למתני אעלה מן החוץ, aidei debai lemisni
amala min hachutz, since it wanted to say that when you bring
it as a sacrifice outside you're not חייב, chayav, so a normal
thing that gets packaged with saying you're not חייב chayav when you
bring it outside the temple is תנא נמי וכולן לא מפיגלין ולא
מתפיגלין, tana nami vechulan lo mapglin velo mitpaglin, it's not פיגול pigul
and you're not חייב chayav outside. So there's throwaway phrases here, it's
not meant to say read this more broadly. And the scenario of
this ברייתא beraita is when you're just thinking about the fetus. But
Rabbi Eliezer would say I would still defend my position, and certainly
you could read it in the משנה, mishna, that if you think
about the mother, the fetus does become פיגול. pigul. Okay, so now
the גמרא gemara says like this, let's wrap this up. רבא אמר
אף אנן נמי תנינא. rava amar af anan nami tenina.
Actually the משנה mishna actually supports Rabbi Eliezer's read, and this is
what I was pointing out to you, that the משנה mishna spoke
about the mother, the milk isn't פיגול, pigul, but it never said
if you think about the mother what the story with the fetus
is. אף אנן נמי תנינא, af anan nami tenina, השוחט את המוקדשים
לאכול שילל או שליה בחוץ לא פיגל. hashocheit et hamukdashim leechol shelil
o shilya bachutz lo pigel. והמולק את התור לאכול ביצים בחוץ לא
פיגל. vehamolek et hatore leechol beitzim bachutz lo pigel. Okay fine, the
eggs. והדר תני, vehadar tani, and then we said when you have
a thought about the mother, חלב המוקדשים וביצי תור אין חייבין עליהם
משום פיגול נותר וטמא. chalav hamukdashim vebeitzat tore ein chayavin aleihem mishum
pigul notar vetamei. That the milk and the eggs are not a
problem. What about the fetus? השליל והשליה חייבי הוו? hashlil vehashilya chayei
havu? It sounds like a thought about the mother, the fetus is?
אלא שמע מינה כאן מחמת זבח כאן מחמת עצמן. ela shema mina
kan machmat zevach kan machmat atzman. Clearly it seems that when your
thought is about the fetus, the fetus is not פיגול, pigul, doesn't
make the mother פיגול, pigul, doesn't make itself פיגול. pigul. But when
the thought is about the mother, the fetus is פיגול. pigul. שמע
מינה, shema mina, and that actually is a very close read of
the משנה. mishna. Okay, so the reason for the asymmetry it seems
is two different reasons. The more sort of elegant case is that
if it's something that's not directed towards the מזבח mizbe'ach or towards
people, it's like the meat that's supposed to be burned outside, a
פיגול pigul thought isn't relevant because it's not misdirecting it. But a
thought about the rest of the animal does or does make this
פיגול pigul because it's part of the animal and so on. The
case of the fetus, it's harder to explain that way because the
fetus normally, you know, it's not like it's if it's edible it's
edible and it's not something that shouldn't be eaten and so on.
So רש"י rashi has to say that that's talking about just the
physical ability to eat. It's considered something that's only edible על ידי
הדחק al yedei hadachak under dire circumstances, and therefore it's not enough
a central part of the things that are eaten that it has
the power to make the mother פיגול, pigul, but when the mother
becomes פיגול, pigul, according to this we would say עובר ירך אמו,
ubar yerech imo, we would say the fetus is part of the
mother according to this approach, and if the mother is פיגול pigul
the fetus is, and it's edible enough to be פיגול. pigul. That's
the way רש"י rashi reads it. If you want to go for
five more minutes we can just hit the משנה. mishna. Okay. תנן
התם. tenan hatam. So this is going to start as a little
digression but it will circle back. ובעלי מומין. uba'alei mumim. When things
that you put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you know, incorrectly, can you
leave them there? There's some things that are so incorrect they have
to be taken down even after they were put. So what's the
story about an animal with a blemish? רבי עקיבא מכשיר בבעלי מומין.
rabbi akiva machshir beva'alei mumim. רבי עקיבא rabbi akiva says if that's
put on the מזבח mizbe'ach it can stay up, others disagree and
say that has to come down. אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר
רבי יוחנן amar rabbi chiya bar abba amar rabbi yochanan לא הכשיר
רבי עקיבא אלא בדוקין שבעין הואיל וכשירים בעופות. lo hichshir rabbi akiva
ela bedukin sheba'ayin ho'il uksherim be'ofot. He would say that that doesn't
apply by a blemish like a missing of a limb because then
that's a complete invalidity. When does he say it, he says that
that's a blemish that's like not a missing limb but like some
cataract of the eye, but it really doesn't even have to be
that subtle. What it really means is any blemish that's not a
missing limb. Why? Because birds, there's no הלכה halacha of unblemished by
birds. The only thing that makes a bird invalid is that it's
missing a limb. So therefore, since by parallel even if this thing's
got a nice big obvious blemish, since were hypothetically were this a
bird it would not be invalid, that's enough to leave it on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach. The only, but if it's missing a limb, then
it has to come down. Okay so that's point number one. And
point number two is והוא
שקדם הקדשה את מומה. vehu shekodem hikdishah et mumah. That's only that
first you sanctified it and then it got the blemish. Okay so
because it was then at one point fit to be on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. So when does רבי עקיבא rabbi akiva say a בעל
מום baal mum can stay? Number one is if first were sanctified
it was fit to be on the מזבח mizbe'ach and then something
happened and the thing that happened at least wouldn't invalidate it if
it had been a bird.
Okay. Now we go on. ומודה רבי עקיבא בעולת נקבה. umodei rabbi
akiva beolat nekeiva. Let's say you sanctified a female animal as an
עולה, olah, he would agree דכמאן דקדם מום להקדשה דמי. dekeman dekodam
mum lehaktaysha dami. That if you put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach
you take it down because the מום mum by this animal, right,
the being a female is a מום. mum. Again, it's not a
statement about females. If you made sanctified
a male for a חטאת chatat or something. Okay, but since it
was always invalid, its physical reality was always invalid, so therefore it
was never fit for the מזבח mizbe'ach as an עולה olah and
therefore it always has to come down. Okay, now,
מתיב רבי זירא. masiv rabbi zeira. So רבי זירא rabbi zeira asked
on them based on the ברייתא beraita we quoted before.
המעלה... hamale... It says that if you put the fetus on the
altar outside of the Temple, right, you're exempt, right? That was that
case before about the fetus and you bring it outside the Temple,
you're exempt. So if we're talking about a fetus, we're talking about
a female, right?
And the things that you're חייב chayav for bringing outside of the
Temple is an עולה. olah. That's what you're חייב chayav for for
bringing outside of the Temple. So it's a very, it's a very
like clear read of this ברייתא. braisa. Wait, we're talking about a
female, but we're talking about bringing it outside the Temple, so we're
talking about an עולה, olah, so we're talking about a female עולה.
olah. Okay, so why are you חייב chayav for female עולה olah
outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, since it wouldn't, it would
never be allowed to even remain on the altar in the בית
המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? האי מאמן, Hai me'iman, if you offered up from
the meat of the mother outside the Temple, חייב, chayav, you're חייב.
chayav. והיכי משכחת לה, Veheichi mashkachat lah, what is the only scenario
we're talking about about חייב chayav for something outside the Temple? An
עולה. olah. But because we're talking about a fetus, we're talking about
a female.
So, והיכי משכחת לה בעולת נקבה? Veheichi mashkachat lah be'olas nekeiva? So
אי אמרת בשלמא כסבר רבי עקיבא עולת נקבה אם עלתה לא תרד.
Ei amart bishlama kasavar Rebbe Akiva olas nekeiva im alsah lo tiered.
So if Rebbe Akiva would hold that if it was put on
the altar a female עולה olah it would stay there, because you're
only חייב chayav outside the Temple for something that in some scenario
could be good in the Temple. So if Rebbe Akiva held in
that case it was put on the altar you wouldn't take it
down, הא מני רבי עקיבא היא. Ha mani Rebbe Akiva hi. This
could be Rebbe Akiva, that's why you're חייב chayav outside the Temple.
אלא אי אמרת אם עלתה תרד, Ela ei amart im alsah tiered,
but if even Rebbe Akiva says in this case it goes down,
so הא מני, Ha mani, who is this going like? This is
something that never would even be allowed to remain on the altar,
so why are you חייב? chayav? So the גמרא Gemara says אימא,
Eima, fine, no, you read the wrong inference. The inference wasn't המעלה
מהם בחוץ פטור, Hamale mehem bachutz patur, הא מאימורי אימן חייב. Ha
me'imurei iman chayav. The inference wasn't that if you put the meat
of this female עולה olah outside of the Temple, you're חייב. chayav.
The inference was if you put the אימורין imurin of this female
of the mother, you're חייב. chayav. Now how does that solve the
problem? Because
it
solves the problem because you're only חייב chayav outside the Temple for
something that is burnt on the altar if you put it up,
if you burn it on a fire. So what is burnt on
the altar? Either the meat of an עולה olah or what else?
The אימורין imurin of any קרבן. korban. So if we were talking
about the meat, the only thing we could be talking about would
be the meat of an עולה olah and it would be a
female עולה olah and that would be our problem. But if we're
talking about the אימורין, imurin, we don't have to be talking about
an עולה. olah. We could be talking like about a שלמים. shelamim.
שלמים shelamim are allowed to be female or a חטאת. chatas. You
with me? So if we're talking about the אימורין, imurin, this isn't
relevant to our discussion, we're not talking about an עולה, olah, and
that's why you're חייב chayav outside the Temple. The גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, והמהן קתני. Veha-mehem katani. It says if you offer them
outside, so how do you switch from talking about them, the fetus,
to the contrast is offering the meat of the mother, not the
אימורין imurin of the mother? ואימן דומיא דידהו. Ve'iman dumya dideyhu. And
the mother isn't parallel. So if we're talking about the fetus you're
not חייב, chayav, the implication is the mother you are חייב. chayav.
אלא אימא, Ela eima, fine, read it this way: המעלה מאימוריהן בחוץ
פטור. Hamale me'imureihen bachutz patur. If you brought offered the אימורין imurin
of the fetus outside, you're פטור, patur, which is so bizarre. Why
would it be talking about the אימורין imurin of the fetus?
הא מאימורי אימן חייב. Ha me'imurei iman chayav. But for the אימורין
imurin of the mother, and the mother wasn't an עולה, olah, it
was a שלמים, shelamim, it was a חטאת, chatas, you'd be חייב.
chayav. So again, a difficult read of the ברייתא. braisa. The simple
reading is yes, that the implication is that you can have a
female עולה olah that you're חייב chayav on outside of the Temple
and that would say that at least somebody would hold that that
would be כשר kosher to remain on the מזבח mizbeach on the
altar in the Temple. Okay, well.